You can do all kinds of fancy stuff with reinforcement
learning, right.
So the crux in reinforcement learning is that
the agent is going to there is this learning
agent right it is going to learn in close
interaction with an environment, right. So
the environment could be the helicopter, it
could be the cycle right and or it could be
your backgammon board and your opponent all
of this could constitute the environment variety
of different choices, so you sense the state
in which the environment is in right.
Sense the state of the environment okay and
figure out what is the action that you should
take in response to the state, right. So when
you apply the action back to the environment
this causes a change in the state right. So
now comes in tricky part right so you should
not just choose actions that are beneficial
in the current state but you should choose
actions in such a way that they will put you
in a state which is beneficial for you in
the future, right.
Just capturing the queen of your opponent
is not enough in chess that might give you
a higher reward but it might put you in a
really bad position, so you do not want that
right you really want to be looking at the
entire sequence of decisions that you are
going to have to make and then try to behave
optimally with respect to that, right. So
what we mean by behave optimally in this case
right we are going to assume that the environment
right is giving you some kind of an evaluation.
It is like falling down hurts when or capturing
a piece maybe gives you a small plus 0.5 or
winning the game gives you like hundred right,
so every time you win every time you make
a move or every time you execute an action
you did not get a reward or you need not get
an evaluation from the environment right so
it could be just zero it could be this could
be nothing, right. So I should point out that
this whole idea of having an evaluation come
from the environment is just a mathematical
convenience that we have here.
But in reality if you think about biological
systems that are learning using reinforcement
learning right all they are getting is the
usual sensory inputs right so there is some
fraction in the brain okay that sits there
and interprets some of those sensory input
as rewards or punishments, right so you fall
down you get hurt I mean that is still a sensory
input that is coming from your skin right
or somebody pats you on your back thats still
a sensory input that comes from the skin.
And it is just another kind of an input right
so you could choose to interpret this as a
reward right or this as a collision with an
obstacle something is brushing against my
shoulder let me move away right or you can
just take it as somebody is patting my back
so I did something good right so it is a matter
of interpretation so this is a this whole
thing about having a state signal and having
a separate evaluation coming from the environment
is a fiction right.
That is created to have a cleaner mathematical
model but in reality things are a lot messier
you know you do not have such a clean separation,
right and like I said so you have a stochastic
environment you have delayed evaluation.
Noisy so the new term that we have added here
is scalar the new term we have added is scalar,
so that is one of the things with the classical
reinforcement learning approaches is that
I am going to assume that my reward is a scalar
signal right so we talked about getting hurt
and having food and so on so forth what will
all of this will happen mathematically is
I will convert that into some kind of a number
on a scale right.
So getting hurt might be minus 100 right getting
food might be plus 5 winning the game might
be plus 20 right capturing a piece might be
plus 0.5 or something like that, so I am going
to convert them to a scale right and the goal
is now that I have a single number that represents
the evaluation the goal is now to get as much
as possible of that quantity over the long
run, okay makes sense right. So if you have
questions, doubts stop me and ask.
So mathematically a scalar is easier to optimize,
not necessarily right I am just talking about
it is like a cost function if you want to
think about it in terms of in terms of control
systems right so this is like a cost and I
am trying to optimize the cost all right and
so if the cost is going to be vector value
then I will have to start trading off one
direction of the vector against the other.
So which component of the vector is more important
so then you get into all kinds of separate
optimality kind of questions so it is not
really clear what exactly is optimal in such
cases right, so in fact later on we have a
homework exercise for you to argue for and
against scalar rewards so you can put on your
thoughts there right, so here again let me
emphasize its not supervised learning right.
In supervise learning this is essentially
what you are going to see there will be an
input and there will be an output that you
are producing and somebody will be giving
you a target output okay so this is what you
are supposed to produce and essentially compare
the output you are producing to the target
output right and we can form some error signal
right and you can use that error in order
to train your agent right.
You can try to minimize the error you can
do gradient descent on the error or you can
do variety of things you can try to train
the agent, so here I do not have a target
I do have to learn a mapping from the input
to the output but I do not have a target and
hence I cannot form an error right and therefore
my trial and error becomes very essential
see if I have errors I can form gradients
of the errors and they can go in the opposite
direction of the gradient of the error, right.
And then that gives me some direction in which
to change my parameters and that constitute
the agent, right agent it is going to be described
in some way right the error gives me a direction
right but now since I do not know a direction
right so I just I do something I get one evaluations
I don't know that the evaluation is good or
bad right so think of writing an exam right
I do not tell you the right answer I just
tell you three right.
And so what do you do now do happy with answer
should you change it should you change it
in one direction or should you change it in
the other direction, so what makes it even
more tricky is I don’t you don’t even
know how much the exam is out of, so when
I say 3 it could be three out of three it
could be three out of 100 right and or it
could be like 3 out of 18 which is what the
class average in ML in the first quiz right.
So it could be any of these things right so
you do not even know whether three is a good
number or a bad number so you have to explore
to figure out a if you can get higher than
three right or three is the best the second
thing is if I can get higher than three how
should I change my parameters to get to become
higher than three right I have to change my
parameters a little bit that way okay.
I have to change the parameter is a little
bit this way right so if I am cycling right
I have to push down a little harder on the
pedal okay or I have to push down a little
softer on the pedal to figure out whether
I am staying balanced for a longer period
of time or not I do not know that otherwise
unless I try these things I would not know
this is why the trial and error part, so if
I pushed down a little harder and I stay balanced
maybe I should try pushing down even more
harder next time right.
So maybe that will make it better and then
there might be some point where I tip over
so I need to come back so this is how things
which you have to try unless you try that
you do not even know which direction you have
to move in right so this is much more than
just the psychological aspects of trial and
error there is also a mathematical reason
if you want to adapt my parameters right I
need to know the gradient okay so that you
will need to look, yeah.
The reward is the one that you know that gives
you the evaluation for the output right so
here in the supervised case the error is the
evaluation for the output if the error is
0 then your output is perfect right but then
we have a way of gauging what the error is
because you have a target to which you can
compare right and from there you get the error
so in the reinforcement learning case the
evaluation is directly given to you as the
evaluation of the output right.
It is not necessarily comparing against target
value or anything you do not know how the
evaluation was generated right you just get
an evaluation directly so you just get some
number corresponding to the output right so
maybe I should have done put an arrow from
the top saying evaluation comes in from there
but that is exactly where it is coming it
is a substitute for the error signal but it
is just that you do not know what the evaluation
is.
Of course the way it differs from the error
is minor difference is you typically tend
to minimize error but you tend to maximize
evaluation right it is also not unsupervised
learning so unsupervised learning you have
some kind of an input right.
That goes to the agent and then it figures
out what are the patterns for the in the input
right here you have some kind of an evaluation
and you are expected to produce an action
in response to the input it is not simply
pattern detection right so you might want
to detect patterns in the input so that you
know what is the right response to give but
that is not the primary goal right but in
unsupervised learning the pattern deduction
itself is the primary goal so that is the
difference right.
So here is this one slide which I think is
kind of the soul of reinforcement learning
right it is called temporal difference so
I will explain it little more detail in a
couple of slides but the intuition here right
so if you remember the Pavlov's dog experiment
right what was the dog doing it was predicting
the outcome of the bell you know if the bell
rings there is an outcome that is going to
happen its predicting the outcome which is
food that is going to happen.
And then it was reacting appropriate to the
outcome right so most of reinforcement learning
you are going to be predicting some kind of
outcome that’s going to happen so am I going
to get a reward if I do this or if am I going
to not get a reward am I going to win this
game if I make this move or am I not going
to win this game all right so I am trying
to always trying to predict the outcome right
the outcome here is the amount of reward or
punishment I am going to get right.
This is essentially what I am trying to predict
at every point right so the intuition behind
what is called temporal difference learning
is the following right so the prediction that
I make at time t+1 okay of what will be the
eventual outcome let us say I am playing a
game right I am going to say I am going to
win now I am very sure I am going to win now
right, so I can say that with a greater confidence
when I am closer to the end of the game.
Than I can at the beginning of the game right
so I have all the pieces set up and if I am
going to sit there and say I am going to win
the game right it is most probably wishful
thinking right but then you have played the
game for like 30 minutes or something and
there are like five pieces left on the board
now I am going to say I am going to win the
game now I say I am going to win the game
that is a much more confident prediction then
what I did at the beginning right.
So taking this to the extreme right so the
prediction I make at t plus 1 is probably
more accurate than the prediction I make at
t, right the prediction I make at t plus 1
is more accurate than the prediction I make
at t, so if I want to improve the prediction
I make a t what can I do I can look go forward
in time basically go to the next step let
the clock tick over and see what is the prediction
I will make a time t plus 1 with additional
knowledge I am getting right.
I would have moved one step closer to the
end of the game so I know a little bit better
about the game right I know how the game is
proceeding I know I can may now make a prediction
about whether I will win or lose right and
use this go back and modify the prediction
I make at time t, right at t I think there
is a possibility of say probability of point
6 of me winning the game okay and then I make
a move then I find out that I am going to
lose the game with a very high probability.
Then what will I do is I will go back and
reduce the probability of winning that I made
at time t so instead of 0.6 I will say okay
maybe .55 or something alright, so next time
I come to the same state as I was at time
t, I would not make the prediction of 0.6
I will say 0.55 okay thats essentially the
idea behind the temporal difference learning,
right. So it is a whole lot of advantages
we will talk about it a couple of slides down.
But one thing is that it has had significant
impact in behavioral psychology and in neuroscience
right so it is widely accepted that animals
actually use some form of temporal difference
learning and in fact there are specific models
right that that have been proposed for temporal
difference learning which seemed to explain
some of the neurotransmitter behaviors in
the brain, yeah. No no no see at this point
I will be making a prediction about what is
the probability of winning.
And it could be for each of the moves right
if I make this move what is the probability
of winning if I make this move what is the
probability of wining, let us say I make move
two okay and then I go I see a new position
right the opponent responds to it and then
I decide oh my god this is a much worse move
than I thought earlier so what I will do is
I will change the prediction I make for move
two in the previous state.
You see that the other moves would not be
affected because the only move t took was
two only about that move I have additional
information therefore I can go back and change
the prediction I make for move two alone,
so you still have the ten moves so you are
not changing any of them. Changing the prediction
its not like I mean if in a ideal world you
should be able to take back a bad move right
except if it is a parent playing with the
kid I do not think those things are allowed
right.
Infact when I play with my son we have sometimes
had to rewind back all the way to the beginning
it will probably be me asking to do the rewinding
not him because he will be drubbing me in
some one of those games but yeah otherwise
you cannot you just make the change the prediction
so next time you play the game you will be
better at it, not for that game well basically
you are messed up. Or you did well I mean
so whatever it is yeah looking at RL right
so lets now look at tic-tac-toe.
How many of you have played tic-tac-toe, good
oh you even you put your hand up okay good
okay good so in tic-tac-toe so you have these
board positions right and so you make different
moves so in the first this is what I have
drawn here is called a game tree right so
I start off with the initial board which is
empty right and there are how many possible
branches there for people making moves nine
possible branches right.
For x has move there are nine possible moves
I have nine possible branches and then for
each of these I will have like eight possible
I am not sure this is the right TV for each
of this I have eight possible branches and
they keep going right so what we are going
to be doing is essentially trying to this
formulate this as a reinforcement learning
problem, so how will you do this as a reinforcement
problem right.
So I have all these board positions right
let us say X is the reinforcement learning
agent and O is the opponent right so initially
given a blank board I will have to choose
one among nine actions right so the the state
that I am going to see is this black the x’s
that goes on the board right and the moves
I will be making are the actions right, so
in the initial position I have nine actions
I make that do I get any reward not really
there is no natural reward signal that you
can give.
Essentially the reward that I am going to
get in this case is if at the end of the moves
if I win I will get a one if I do not win
I get a zero and if I win I get a one if I
do not win I get a zero right so what is going
to happen is I am going to keep playing these
games multiple times right and at each point
right yeah okay so there is a note here so
what is it not say we ought to assume it is
an imperfect opponent right.
Otherwise there is no point in trying to learn
tic-tac-toe why, they will always draw and
the way we have set up the game you are indifferent
between drawing and losing so you learn nothing
I mean basically so you will not know even
learn to draw okay you will just learn to
nothing basically you learn nothing because
you can never win right so you are never going
to get a reward of 1 so it will just be playing
randomly.
So it is it is a bad idea so let us assume
that you have an agent that is that is imperfect
right that makes mistakes so that you can
actually learn to figure out where the agent
makes mistakes where the opponent makes mistakes
and learn to exploit those things okay, right.
So your states are going to be this board
positions as you can see we give you see a
game that has been played out on the top of
the slide right and the actions you take are
in response to those board positions.
And finally at the end of the game and if
you win you get a 1 if you do not win you
get a 0, right. Sir in cases like this there
could be a binary sort of a reward system
so could you have a scale where there are
3 parameters if you lose its0, if you draw
its 0.5 and if you win its 1. Sure you could
even do other things like if you win it is
one if you lose it is minus 1 so then if you
have a perfect opponent can you learn ..yeah
you possibly could but you probably have to
play a lot and lot of games because the perfect
opponent it is almost impossible for you to
start getting any feedback in the beginning
right you will always be losing.
So it is going to be hard for it to learn
but you will eventually learn something yeah
it will take a lot of time mostly you will
learn something if I say that at every point
so. When we are learning like at a particular
stage the probability of winning and like
you are having to update so your storing information
for you are storing information for each and
every state that you have entered right so
how will it be different from exploring the
proper know like state space every time.
Because after you have done let us say a thousand
ten thousand games or a million games you
really explored a lot of states and you have
to store for each state the probability of
you winning at that point yeah and all that
so how will that be different from exploring
it again like I know the probability of winning
from there why would I have to explore .. still
I have not even told you how we are going
to solve it okay let me explain that and then
you can come back and ask me these questions
okay if you still have it okay great.
So what the way we are going to try and solve
this game is as follows right for every board
position I am going to try and estimate the
reward I will get if I start from there and
play the game to the end, right every board
position I am going to look at the reward
I will get if I start from there and play
till the end, now if you think about it what
will this reward connote connotate right.
So if I win from there I will get a 1 if I
lose from there or if I do not win from that
I will get a 0 right, when I say what is the
reward I expect to get starting from this
board position right it is essentially this
average over multiple games in some games
I will win some games I will lose I or I will
not win like some games I win some games I
will not win so what will this expected reward
represent.
After having played many many games, the probability
of winning right the reward is going to represent
the probability of winning in this particular
case right if the reward had not been one
right if it had been something else if it
had been plus 5 right it would have been some
function of the probability of winning right
or of it had been plus 1 for winning minus
1 for loosing and 0 for draw well it is something
more complex.
It is no longer the probability of winning
right it is the gain i expect to get right
how much what fraction of games I expect to
win over the fraction of games I expect to
lose or something like that right it becomes
a little bit more complex, so that there could
be some interpretation for the value function
but in general it is just the expected reward
that I am going to get starting from a particular
board position okay.
So that is what I am trying to estimate right
let us assume that I have such a expectation
well defined for me right as I say I have
such an expectation well defined right now
I come to a specific position let us say I
come to this position here let us say I come
to this position how will I decide what is
the next move I have to make, sorry whichever
next state has the highest probability of
winning.
So I just look ahead to see okay where if
I put if I put the X here right if I put the
X here what is the probability of winning
if I put the X here what is the probability
of winning if i put the X here what is the
probability of winning right and I do this
for each one of these right and then I figure
out which ever has the highest probability
of winning and I will put the X there alright
so that is how I am going to use this function.
Does it make sense yes it is very important
so this is this is something which you should
understand this is the crux of all reinforcement
learning algorithms right I am going to learn
this function that tells me if you are in
this state right if you play things out to
the end what will be the expected payoff that
you will get right whether the rewards or
punishment or cost whatever you want to call
it what is the expected value you are going
to get and when I want to behave according
to a this learned function.
So when I come to a state I look ahead figure
out which of the next States has the highest
expectation and then go to that state okay,
great how do I learn this expectation. What
is the simplest way to learn the expectation,
this is essentially you keep track of what
happens essentially you keep track of the
trajectory through the game tree right you
play a game you go all the way to the end
right so you keep track of the trajectory
and if you win right you go back along the
trajectory and update every state that you
saw on the trajectory.
You update the probability of winning right
you just increase it a little bit or you come
to the end of the game and you found that
you have not won right you go back along the
trajectory you decrease the probability of
winning a little bit right alternatively you
can keep the history of all the games you
have played so far right at every after every
game has been completed you can go back and
compute the average probability of winning
across the entire history of all the games
in which you saw that particular position
right make sense that’s easiest way of estimating
this probability right but the problem with
this is A you have to wait till the game ends
right or you have to store the history of
all the games you have played right all of
these could be potential drawbacks okay you
can get around the history part by coming
up with an incremental rule but the main difficulty
here is you have to wait all the way to the
end of the game right before you can change
anything along the way.
So tic-tac-toe is easy like how many moves
can you make in tic-tac-toe at best, four
right the fifth one is determined for you
and so it is basically four choices that you
can make right there so and that is easy enough
to remember right you can always wait till
the end of the game and then you can always
make the updates right what if it's a much
more complex situation right what if you are
playing chess.
Maybe you can wait till the end so what if
you are cycling maybe you can wait till end,
exactly he we do not know right it depends
on where your cycling if you are cycling learning
to cycle in IIT Madras it is fine when you
are learning to cycle somewhere on the sardar
patel road you do not want to even think about
what end is there right so there are some
tasks for which you really like to learn along
the way right.
So this is where TD learning comes into it
comes to help right I do not think I have
a slide anyway and I am not using the fancy
thing where I can draw on the on the projection
so let us see if I can do it here right suppose
I have come here right and from here I have
played at this point I know the probability
of winning is say 0.4 right so I came here
by making a move from this position.
So I said we were here right and we made a
we know that the probability of winning from
here is 0.3 right but I made the move from
here to come here right but here I had thought
my probability of winning was let us say 0.6
right I thought my probability of winning
was 0.6 right but then I looked at my next
states and I found that the best one was 0.3
somehow right so I went there right but now
since the best I can do from here is 0.3 me
saying 0.6 here there is something wrong right
so I should probably decrease the probability
of winning from here right.
So why could it be why could it have happened
that I thought that was 0.6 but the best among
the next was 0.3 may be the other 0.4 that
was fully explored all of that… the thing
is so that whenever I came to came through
this part right maybe I won before right that
it so happened that when I went through like
this right initially I would have gone through
like this and played the game the examples
I drew I might have actually won some of those
games right.
So I would have changed this to 0.6 right
but it is possible for me to get here by playing
a different sequence of moves also right so
for example to come here right I could have
put the X first here and then here or I could
have put the X like I did here I put the X
first here and then here right either way
I would have reached this position right so
there are many combinations in which I could
have reached the same positions right its
just to be nice to these guys right to reach
here there are different orders in which I
could have put the zeros and the Xs right
here we are showing a specific order now 0
first 1st put here then put here then the
x was first put here then put in here it could
very well be I put the X first here and the
o first here and then I put the X here and
the O here right there could be multiple ways
in which this thing was reached right.
So sometimes when I play those games right
I lost right sometimes when I play these games
I won therefore it turns out that for due
to some random fluctuations right so sometimes
I win when I go through this specific point
and therefore I have a higher evaluation of
winning right but when I went through the
other paths I had a lower evaluation of winning
right but we know that really does not matter
what path you went through in tic-tac-toe
right once your each that point right what
is going to happen further is determined only
by that point right.
So what I can do now is take this point 3
right use it to update that
0.6 down so I am very confident here I think
I will win with the probability of 0.6 right
but the best probability I have from the next
stage is 0.3 therefore here i should not be
so confident right good point that depends
on how stochastic your game is right so if
your game has a lot of variability then you
do not want to make a complete you know commitment
to .3 so you might want to say okay now let
me move it little bit towards 0.3 right but
if it is a more or less a deterministic game
then you can say okay yeah 0.3 yes sure let
me go to all the way 0.3 it depends on the
nature of the game we will talk about these
issues later there but how far down is a tricky
thing yeah it is misleading it is called game
tree usually but it is a game graph in this
case yeah .
So as I said when this is this is an instance
of temporal difference learning so how well
I use the thing to update this is called temporal
difference learning ok so there is one other
thing which i Should mention here right if
I always take the move that which I think
is the best move right now right let us talk
about it I start tabula rasa I never played
tic-tac-toe before right so I play the game
I play it once I get to the end I win so now
what I do I go back right whether I am using
temporal difference learning or waiting till
the end up dating whatever it is I change
the value of all the moves I have made in
this particular game right.
So the next time I come to a board position
what am I going to do I look at all possible
outcomes everything except the one that I
have played will have a 0 right and the one
that I have played will have something slightly
higher than 0 I am going to take that in fact
it will be like how many of you watch the
movie Groundhog Day it will be like Groundhog
Day I will be playing I will be playing the
same game again and again because that is
what happened to give me a win in the first
time around right that but that might not
be the best way to play this right.
So I need to explore right so I need to explore
multiple options right so I should not be
always playing the best best move room right
I should not always be playing the best move
I need to do some amount of exploration so
that I can figure out if there are better
moves than what I think is currently the best
move right so tic-tac-toe there is inherently
some kind of noise if your opponent is random
right but if your opponent is not random right
if your opponent is also playing a fixed rule
and if you are playing greedy then you will
be just playing a very very small fraction
of the game tree and you would not have explored
the rest of the outcomes right.
So you have to do some amount of things at
random so that you learn more about the game
right so here is a question for you when I
am estimating this probabilities of winning
right let us say I have reached here I look
down right and the action that gives me the
highest probability of winning say gives me
a probability of say 0.8 right but I want
to explore right so I take an action that
gives me a probability say 0.4 okay so I will
go from here to another action that has a
probability 0.4 another board position that
has a probability of 0.4 of winning so should
I use this 0.4 to update this probability
or not no why that you are questioning the
whole TD idea yeah okay any other answer you
have to update because you are learning that
whether it good or a bad move will be found
out.
I have to update the value of that move I
agree do I update the value of winning from
the previous board position was the question
so that 0.4 I will have to change right but
do I change the 0. 8 that was a question the
0.8 was the probability of winning from here
right I look or whatever the probability say
I had a probability of winning of 0.6 from
here I look at the bottom and the best probability
of winning says 0.8 but then I take because
I am exploring I would take an action that
has a probability of winning of 0.4.
Right the question is do I go back and change
the 0.6 towards 0.4 or do I leave the 0.6
as it is sorry I am exploring right I mean
this is will necessarily be less than 0.8
this will be 0 .4 that will be 0.6 so the
question here is see one way of arguing about
this is to say that hey if I am playing to
win right I will play the best action from
here right and the best action says 0.8 therefore
I should not penalize it for the bad action
which is 0.4 which I did to learn more about
the system.
That is one way of thinking about it another
way of arguing is to say that hey no no this
is how I am actually behaving now right so
I should give you the probability of winning
about the current behavior policy right this
should not be some other ideal policy this
should be about what I am behaving currently
and therefore I should update it right so
which one is correct first or the second you
do not know what the second you would say
the second one great so all of you can go
right that in your homework answers.
Okay I think this is one of the homework questions
as well right are you looking at the question
I know you are browsing you are not paying
attention to me but can you look at the questions
as well you do not have network here is it
Icsr network does not work okay there should
be a Wi-Fi access point called ICSr studio
or something no fine do you have the question
we have the book offline I do believe this
one of the questions right so otherwise make
up a question and write the answer to that
so we will feel will make sure this is one
of the questions but this is something these
are this is like I said I am going to ask
you to think about the whole tic-tac-toe thing
and many of these answers have relevance later
on in fact there are two different algorithms
one does option one and one does option two.
Right so there is no right answer or wrong
answer right answer is depends yeah so yeah
so this is how different things that you can
think about in this but I told you about two
different ways of learning with tic-tac-toe
one wait till the end and figure out what
the probabilities will be the other one this
keep adapting this as you go along right and
both cases you will have to explore that is
the tricky part here in both cases you have
to explore otherwise you will not learn about
the entire game so this is where the explore
exploit thingy comes in okay yeah sir how
do you know at what point you stop exploring
and start exploiting great question different
algorithms deal with it different way that
is one of the crucial questions that you have
to answer in RL.
So it is called the Explore exploit dilemma
right so you have to explore to find out which
is the best action right and you have to exploit.
)
Whatever knowledge you have gathered right
and you have to act according to the best
observations already made right so this is
called exploitation right so the key was the
key questions is when do you know you have
explored enough right should I explore now
or should I exploit now this is called the
Explore exploit dilemma right and a slightly
simpler version of reinforcement learning
called the Bandit problems okay some colorfully
called bandit problems yeah of course he is
an expert on bandit problems here you can
the Bandit problems encapsulate this Explore
exploit dilemma.
My god lot of people are turning and looking
at you subo and so this is the next chapter
we are going to look at this so probably in
the next class I will start plunging into
bandit problems in more detail but so this
will ignore a whole bunch of other things
like the delayed rewards you know the sequential
decisions and other things even in the absence
of all of these other complications right
even if I say that you are all your problem
is you have to take an action and you will
get a reward okay your goal is to pick the
action that gives the highest reward.
I will give you 10 actions you have to pick
the action that gives you the highest reward
right but the problem is you do not know what
is the probability distribution from which
these rewards are coming right so you will
have to do some exploration I have to actually
do every action at least once okay to know
what will be the reward even if they are deterministic
right so I cannot say which is the best action
before I try every action at least once if
it is deterministic it is fine I can just
try every action once and I know what is the
payoff right but if it is stochastic I have
to try every action multiple times right.
How many times do you have to try it depends
on the variability of the distribution right
so these are the subtle questions which we
will talk about as we look at the next chapter
in the first chapter in the book the first
real chapter in the book okay there is an
intro chapter which talks about tic tac toe
and a whole bunch of other things and yeah
you ever stop soon not sure whether we can
do all of this yeah so we will come back and
talk about all of this later right so I thought
I would not spend enough time talking about
the general background of RL applications
so I put in a little bit more slides I typically
do this on the board right.
So I will do this on the board when I get
to chapter 3 right and so one thing which
I wanted to tell you was this right there
are you know two classes of algorithms that
we will be talking about so one of them is
based on what is called dynamic programming
right.
)
So dynamic programming how many of you know
what dynamic programming is I expect at least
23 hands up and I have mechanical engineers
putting their hands up not the CS guys really
you don’t know what dynamic programming
is something wrong with your hand then okay
fine so what this essential idea behind dynamic
I will talk again I will talk as as usual
with other things we will dwell in this in
larger detail the essential idea behind dynamic
programming is you will be using some kind
of repeated structure in the problem right.
So and to solve the problem more efficiently
right suppose I have a solution that I can
give for a problem of say size n right then
I will try to see if I can use that for defining
the solution for the problem of size n plus
1 so some kind of a repeated sub structure
in the problems right very very rough way
of describing what dynamic programming is
right so for example one way of thinking about
dynamic programming is I have this game tree
right so I look at the values of winning or
the expectations of winning from all of these
steps right.
)
I will use these in order to compute the value
of winning or the probability of winning from
this state right so if you think about it
if from here if I'm going to take say n steps
from here how many steps will you expect me
to take n minus 1 steps right so I look at
the probability of winning when I when I have
only n minus 1 steps left right I will estimate
that first I will use that solution for estimating
the probability of winning when I have n steps
left right so that is essentially the idea
behind dynamic programming and so what we
will do is well we will talk about how do
you use dynamic programming to solve reinforcement
learning problems right.
And then we will talk about various reinforcement
learning methods which are essentially online
approximate dynamic programming you know so
they are they use dynamic programming ideas
but they do not have any knowledge of the
system dynamics right so the P and R and other
things become clear later and so all you do
now is instead of having the entire outcome.
)
And using that for estimating the probability
of winning here right I am going to just use
one step that I take through the tree right
I use just what happens in this one step I
will use that in order to update the probability
of winning here right instead of using the
entire outcome right as in dynamic programming
in reinforcement learning methods we will
be using samples that you are getting through
the state space.
This is the TD method in the other method
I explained to in for tic-tac-toe what would
you do your sample will run all the way to
the end right and you use that to update so
this is the two different ways of using samples
here so if you are doing it for the first
time right first time down the tree there
will be no updates actually because S t plus
1 will also be 0 St will also be 0 the first
time we go down there will be no updates but
once you reach an end then from there you
will start updating the previous state.
So the next time you go down the tree then
it will keep going further up whether you
won the game or lost the game I actually I
am taking the exact outcome that happened
in that particular trial right at that particular
game and I use that to change my probabilities
right but here I am not just taking the outcome
of that particular game right I am looking
at the expected value of winning from the
next board position right so if I wait till
all the way here and I say I won and i take
this and update St then I will be only updating
it with the fact that whether I won or not
okay but if I am updating it from S t plus
1 see I could have reached this S t plus 1
in multiple ways before right
When I am doing the updation from S t plus
1 it is essentially the average accumulated
over all the previous trials that I will be
using right so if I play all the way to the
end and update it will be with a one or a
zero but S t plus 1 could be anywhere between
1 and 0 depending on what is the probability
of winning,.
So I will be using that value for updation
that is a crucial difference I so there are
many different solution methods so there are
all this which are called temporal difference
methods.
)
So these are all different algorithms TD lambda
Q learning SARSA actor critic so on so forth
right and then there is this whole search
of algorithms which are called policy search
algorithms and then there is dynamic programming
so we will actually look at each of these
classes of algorithms in the in the next few
lectures right these are all essentially mostly
from the textbook except policy search algorithms
which I will be covering from other material
right and then whole bunch of other applications
for RL right.
)
So you could they are all over the place as
you could see optimal control combinatorial
optimization OR psychology neuroscience so
that is one of the reasons I was asking you
whether there was anyone from biotech because
biotech people do use reinforcement learning
a lot and usually there are one or two people
in the RL class so this is a surprise or maybe
there was a biotech registrant according to
the academic website I mean they just came
up in CS 36 and went back I do not know right.
)
So here is the most recent hot thing that
comes from came from RL right more game playing
and for a change is not from IBM its from
Google but the company that actually built
the first this arcade game playing engine
was called deep mind and as soon as deep mind
built a successful engine Google bought them
right and so now it is Google deep mind but
it is a separate entity right it is not part
of Google. Google deep mind operates out of
London and they are doing all kinds of interesting
stuff many of the hot advances and very recent
advances in the last year or so in reinforcement
learning seem to be coming out of deep mind.
So what they did was how many of you know
about this Atari games right everyone knows
about Atari games people are getting tired
really no one has played pacman yeah how about
how about pong breakout space invaders come
on yeah anyway so what happened was this is
team in University of Alberta ok which put
out this their what they call the ALE the
arcade learn the Atari learning environment
or arcade learning environment which essentially
they allowed computers to play these games
right these Atari games and what the deep
mind fellows came up with is a reinforcement
agent that learned to play this game from
scratch just by looking at the screen.
Okay that is all the input it was getting
just the pixels from the screen they are all
pixels on the screen are given as inputs to
it used a very complex neural network so it
is a deep learning deep network right and
it is considered one of the hardest learning
problems solved by a computer and I believe
it is a one the only computational reinforcement
learning paper ever to appear in nature right
so usually is very hard for non natural science
people to publish in nature kind of obvious
right it is usually hard for the computer
science folks to publish in nature but this
was touted as the next step in trying to understand
how humans process inputs blah all kinds of
marketing jargon right but more importantly
than anything else about this its reproducible.
So I told you about I think that is a warning
sign for me to stop so I told you about the
helicopter right so there is basically Stanford
and Berkeley are the two people who get the
helicopter to fly I told you about the backgammon
player its like Jerry Tesauro is the one person
who gets the backgammon player to work right
partly because all the input features he uses
in there or proprietary but partly because
it’s a very hard problem to solve right
what is amazing thing about this Atari game
engine is that these guys have released the
code right you can if you have enough powerful
GPUs right you can set it up here and get
it to play and get a reasonably working engine
right.
That plays those Atari games that's the amazing
thing about it that is reproducible as opposed
to many of the other things other success
stories other success stories we have had
in the past so I do believe I had just one
more slide after this so let us see if this
will work.
)
Okay so if you have any doubts the green one
is the learning agent no no this is just sped
up for you to see you mean it is not like
the game is progressing at the same rate but
you can see the scores though mind you it
was not given a reward okay it is just given
the screen never got a reward for winning
or anything it has to understand that the
pixels on the top are rewarding and if we
give it rewards it becomes cheating right
or is it which is what they did they did they
did add a game over which is which the ALE
purists considered as cheating but they did
add a game over sign so the longer you keep
it going the better it is basically I think
this is getting boring right.
So it is learnt here
so this is a sea quest you have to swim and
then sink down get some things and come up
so sea quest is a game that it never learned
to do greatly on and sea quest is not something
which it learn to solve well so there are
a few games like this so they initially published
the nature paper I think they had like 45
or 46 out of the 50 ale games they were able
to play well and I think in 43 of them it
had better than human performance and I think
the current state is they have like one game
that doesn't play well right and have better
than human performance in like 48 of those
games or something.
So is this is amazing if you think about it
right so these are all lot of references but
we will be using the Sutton and Barto textbook
the second edition we there is a pre-release
copy which rich Sutton is continuously updating
on his webpage right and the very short introduction
to reinforcement learning in Tom Mitchell's
book and there is a chapter in Russell and
norwig and if you are interested in looking
at the neuroscience perspective of reinforcement
learning or the history of how behavioral
psychology models evolved to temporal difference
learning you can look at Dayan and Abbott
it is one chapter on reinforcement learning
you do not have to understand the neuroscience
to understand the RL chapter.
So do not get put off by the title of the
book right and then the more mathematically
well grounded introduction to reinforcement
learning would be from Bertsekas and Tsitsiklis
so apart from this we will use one book which
is Markov decision processes by Puterman that
will use certain chapters from Puterman right
they are just for us to understand MDPs better
markov decision processes better.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved